<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A consolatory discourse for the support of distressed widows and orphans of general use to all Christians who either are or may be left in such circumstances.</title>
            <author>Camfield, Benjamin, 1638-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32785</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C378</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35835</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15564942</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15564942</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103800</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32785)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103800)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1588:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A consolatory discourse for the support of distressed widows and orphans of general use to all Christians who either are or may be left in such circumstances.</title>
                  <author>Camfield, Benjamin, 1638-1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Newton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: B. Camfield.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Camfield by Wing.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed and entred according to order."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103800:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Conſolatory Diſcourſe For the ſupport of Diſtreſſed WIDOWS AND ORPHANS: Of General uſe to all Chriſtians, who either are, or may be, left in ſuch Circumſtances.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm XL. 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>As for me, I am poor and needy; But the Lord thinketh upon [or <hi>careth for</hi>] me.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm CXIX. 49.50.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Remember the Word unto thy Servant, upon which thou haſt cauſed me to hope.</p>
               <p>This is my comfort in my affliction; for thy word hath quickened me.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm XCIV. 19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>In the multitude of my thoughts within me thy comforts delight my Soul.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lament. III. 21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>This I recall to my mind, therefore have I hope. It is of the Lords mercies that we are not conſumed, becauſe his compaſſions fail not.</p>
               <p>They are new every morning: Great is thy Faithfulneſs.</p>
               <p>The Lord is my Portion, ſaith my Soul; Therefore will I hope in him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Licenſed and Entred according to Order.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Newton,</hi> at the three <hi>Pigeons,</hi> over againſt the Inner-<hi>Temple-Gate</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:103800:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103800:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have only to <hi>pre-admoniſh,</hi> that this ſmall Treatiſe is deſigned for the Conſolation of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and Vertuous;</hi> they are the perſons who have the ſecurity of <hi>God Almighty's peculiar Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence over, and moſt Gracious promiſes to them.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">He is nigh unto the righteous, his eyes are upon them, and his ears are open unto their cry, to deliver them out of all their Troubles; and none of them ſhall be deſolate: <hi>Pſ. 34.15,</hi> &amp;c.] All things ſhall work to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for good to them that love God: <hi>[Rom. 8.28.]</hi> To them he will be better than a Father, and Mother, and Husband, [<hi>2 Cor. 6.18. Pſ. 123.13. Iſa. 66.13. Iſa. 49.15.—54.4.</hi> &amp;c.] They are the Poor and Broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, whom he ſendeth good tidings to; <hi>They</hi> the mourners whom he will have comforted, <hi>[Iſa. 61.1, 2, 3.]</hi> Comfort ye, comfort ye my People, <hi>(ſaith your God,)</hi> ſpeak ye comfortably to <hi>Jeruſalem, [Ch. 40.1.]</hi>
               </q>—As for others, though they partake of the ſcatterings of his Common Bounty, <q rend="inline">who maketh his Sun to riſe on the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and on the Good, and ſendeth Rain on the Juſt and on the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, <hi>(St. Mat. 5.45.)</hi> and are accordingly, the Objects of our general charity alſo in their extreme ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities,
<pb facs="tcp:103800:3"/>who, as we have opportunity, muſt follow that pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of doing good to all; yet they fall not under that more ſpecial regard, which God himſelf beareth, and hath commanded us in like manner to expreſs, <hi>to the Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of Faith, [Gal. 6.10.]</hi>—The truth is, as they are not capable of theſe divine Conſolations, ſo they as little mind or reliſh them; and the Apoſtle ſpeaking of that ſort of Widows, ſaith, <hi>they are dead while they live, 1 Tim. 5.6.]</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <q>And now there will not need an <hi>Apologie,</hi> I hope, for committing of theſe Papers to the Preſs, any more than for contributing towards a publick Benefit, and putting it into the hands of many to gratifie their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Friends, at a very ſmall expence, with what may prove a Cordial to their Spirits beyond any other; at leaſt will add conſiderably to thoſe other, ſupplies they are able to afford for their relief.—This I will ſay, for their greater encouragement, that nothing is here offer'd, which affects the Differences and Diſputes among ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſocieties of Chriſtians, as now they ſtand unhappily divided; but only what is agreeable to their common Sentiments, and that good Profeſſion wherein they all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree together, and I know not of any ſuch entire Collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the Subject, as is to be found in the enſuing Pages.—Which that they may obtain the end, whereunto they are intended, is the earneſt deſire of the Compiler and Publiſher, who is an hearty Lover of all ſincere Chriſtians, and zealouſly concern'd for the Widows and Fatherleſs among them; from whoſe Prayers and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings he expects an abundant retribution.</q>
            <closer>
               <signed>B. Camfield.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103800:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Scripture Conſolations</hi> FOR DISTRESSED WIDOWS AND ORPHANS.</head>
            <p>HAVING had occaſion lately, with a more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ſenſe and compaſſion, to reflect upon the <hi>diſconſolate eſtate of poor diſtreſſed Widows, and their Fatherleſs Children,</hi> (Three Families of my <hi>Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and</hi> thoſe of the <hi>Clergy too,</hi> being fallen, in leſs than the ſpace of a year, under that heavy affliction,) I have for <hi>their ſakes chiefly,</hi> and thoſe that <hi>may be reduced to the like calamity,</hi> on purpoſe collected <hi>ſuch Scripture comforts, as relate more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to their ſad and mournful condition;</hi> and do now moſt heartily recommend the ſame unto their <hi>frequent peruſal and ſerious meditations,</hi> That they may learn, <hi>In Patience to poſſeſs their Souls,</hi> and <hi>through comfort of the Scriptures to have hope.</hi>
               <note place="margin">St. Luke. 21.19. Rom. 15.4.</note> For which care alſo, <hi>I bow my knees to the Father of all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and compaſſions, that his Grace and Bleſſing may accompany theſe well meant endeavours to their hearts, and</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">That he would grant them, according to the riches of his Glory,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.16. Coloſ. 1.11.</note> to be ſtrengthned with might, by his ſpirit in the inward man unto all long-ſuffering with joyfulneſs.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:103800:4"/>
            <p>Were not <hi>Divine Providence</hi> particularly concerned in taking care for <hi>ſuch Objects of Charity,</hi> the World <hi>it ſelf could hardly ſubſiſt in any tolerable ſtate,</hi> abounding with ſo <hi>many inſtances of them in every Age and Place:</hi> But then the <hi>aſſurance of this good Providence</hi> is no where to be had with <hi>like advantage,</hi> both of <hi>certainty and fulneſs,</hi> as from that <hi>Book of Books,</hi> that inexhauſtible Fountain and Treaſure of choiceſt Conſolations, <hi>the Holy word of God.</hi> From <hi>whence</hi> therefore,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I obſerve, That God is pleaſed to repreſent himſelf, as delighting in the Title of <hi>their peculiar Friend and Patron,</hi> and deſirous to be known and glorified by it. He <hi>proclaimed this by</hi> Moſes <hi>of old to the</hi> Iſraelites, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.17, &amp;c. <q rend="inline">The Lord your God is God of Gods, and Lord of Lords, a Great God, and a Mighty, and a Terrible, who regardeth not Perſons, nor taketh reward: He doth execute the Judgment of the Fatherleſs and Widow, and loveth the Stranger, in giving him Food and Raiment;</q> and the <hi>ſenſe of this is often repeated in the Pſalms, and elſewhere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pſalm 10.14. <q rend="inline">The Poor committeth himſelf unto thee; Thou art the helper of the Fatherleſs, [or Friendleſs,] And again, <hi>ver.</hi> 17.18. Lord, thou haſt heard the deſire of the humble, [or Poor,] Thou wilt prepare [or eſtabliſh] their heart, Thou wilt cauſe thine Ear to hear; To judge [or help] the Fatherleſs and oppreſſed to their right, that the Men of the Earth be no more exalted againſt them.</q> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. [A Pſalm <hi>in imitation of that of</hi> Moſes <hi>at the ſetting forward of the Ark,</hi> Numb. 10.35. and <hi>formed by King</hi> David, <hi>probably on like occaſion,</hi> at the bringing up the ſame from the houſe of <hi>Obed. Idem.</hi>] <hi>ver.</hi> 4. and 5. <q rend="inline">Extoll him that rideth upon the Heavens, by his name <hi>Jah,</hi> and rejoyce before him. A Father of the Fatherleſs, and a Judge of the Widows, is God in his holy Habitation.</q>—His name <hi>Jah</hi> (a contract of <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah</hi>) ſignifies his <hi>neceſſary Exiſtence;</hi> and <hi>as certainly as he is,</hi> he will ſhew himſelf alſo a <hi>Father of the Fatherleſs, and a Judge of the Widows; to hear and defend their Cauſe;</hi> And, though he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103800:4"/>inhabits the <hi>higheſt Heaven,</hi> yet he is pleaſed here <hi>below</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit himſelf in a peculiar manner the <hi>Protector and Patron of ſuch diſtreſſed ones,</hi> Pſalm 72.12, 13, 14. <q rend="inline">He ſhall deliver the needy when he cryeth, the Poor alſo, and him that hath <hi>no helper.</hi> He ſhall ſpare the Poor and Needy, and ſhall ſave the Souls of the needy. He ſhall redeem their Soul from deceit and violence, and precious ſhall their bloud be in his ſight.</q> It is ſpoken of <hi>God our Saviour,</hi> the <hi>Meſſias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Hammond in Loc.</hi>
               </note> whoſe Kingdom is there reſembled to the Government of a <hi>juſt and mercifull Prince,</hi> that is ready to relieve all that are oppreſſed and wronged; <hi>A Prince of bowels and compaſſions,</hi> to them that are in any kind of diſtreſs, to defend and deliver them out of it, to reſcue them from the hands of the injurious and Oppreſſor, and preſerve their lives from all that invade them, as perſons that are <hi>much valued and highly eſteemed by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146. Having repreſented the variety of depending upon the <hi>beſt of mortal Men,</hi> who at death muſt needs fail, and all their projects with them; He goes on to proclaim <hi>their happineſs, who have the Eternal God of Heaven and Earth for their Helper;</hi> of whom he <hi>farther adds</hi> for their encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>ver.</hi> 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Who executeth Judgment for the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, who giveth food to the hungry; The Lord looſeth the Priſoners; The Lord openeth the Eyes of the blind; The Lord raiſeth them that are bowed down; The Lord loveth the righteous, <hi>[or careth for the righteous;]</hi> The Lord preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the Strangers, he releiveth [or <hi>defendeth</hi>] the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and Widow; But the way of the wicked he turneth upſide down.—</q> The ſenſe of all which is, that it is <hi>God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s peculiar property to interpoſe his Aid moſt ſeaſonably, when our Diſtreſſes are the greateſt;</hi> To undertake the defence and patronage of thoſe, who are moſt unjuſtly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd; To work even <hi>Miracles of mercy for them that ſtand in moſt need of them,</hi> ſignally to expreſs his favour to <hi>pious and charitable minded Men,</hi> in all their neceſſities, and under all their reſtraints, and afflictions; and, if there be any <hi>more deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute than other,</hi> more ſhut out from all ſorts of humane ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103800:5"/>as thoſe that have <hi>neither Houſe, nor Parent, nor Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to relieve and comfort them, [the Stranger, the Fatherleſs, the Widow:]</hi> Theſe are the firſt Objects of his Grace and Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, of whom he will have a <hi>peculiar care,</hi> if in the abſence of worldly aids they ſincerely apply themſelves, and conſtantly adhere to his Obedience; he will never leave, or forſake them. <q rend="inline">When my Father and Mother forſake me, the Lord will take me up,</q> 
               <hi>ſaith the Pſalmiſt in another place,</hi> Pſal. 27.10. And again, <q rend="inline">I have been young, and now am old; yet have I not ſeen the Righteous forſaken, nor his Seed begging bread.</q> 
               <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37.25. I will cloſe this with <hi>that ſignificant expreſſion of the Prophet,</hi> Hoſea 14.3. <q rend="inline">In thee the Fatherleſs findeth mercy.</q>
            </p>
            <p>So then, by <hi>this gracious Style and Title</hi> which God aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes to himſelf, he <hi>ſaith plainly</hi> to his Servants, and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, what the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> relates as ſpoken of, or unto <hi>Edom,</hi> (it may be in ſome different ſenſe,) <hi>Jer.</hi> 49.11. <q rend="inline">Leave thy Fatherleſs Children, I will preſerve them alive; and let thy Widows truſt in me.</q>
            </p>
            <p>—<q rend="inline">He will eſtabliſh the border of the Widow, <hi>ſaith</hi> Solomon,</q> 
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.25. And again, <q rend="inline">Enter not into the Fields of the Fatherleſs, for their Redeemer is mighty; he will plead their cauſe with thee.</q> 
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 23.10, 11. to which effect alſo he had ſaid before, <q rend="inline">Rob not the poor becauſe he is poor, neither oppreſs the afflicted in the Gate; for the Lord will plead their cauſe, and ſpoil the Soul of thoſe that ſpoiled them,</q> 
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.22, 23.</p>
            <p>And here I call to mind <hi>a memorable paſſage of</hi> Tertullian, in a Book written to his <hi>own Wife,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad uxorem.</hi> L. 1. C. 8.</note> where having quoted <hi>that of the Prophet</hi> Iſaiah, <hi>Ch.</hi> 1. <q rend="inline">[Judge the Fatherleſs, Plead for the Widow; come now and let us reaſon together,]</q> as a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient inſtance of the <hi>honour and eſteem God hath for Widows,</hi> He adds, that theſe two names, (viz. <q rend="inline">the <hi>Fatherleſs, and Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows,</hi>) are no leſs open to the <hi>Divine mercy,</hi> than they are expoſed to <hi>humane contempt;</hi> and that the <hi>Father of all hath undertaken the Tuition of them:</hi> See, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> how favourably he is look'd upon, who hath <hi>done the Widows a good turn.</hi> But then, how
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103800:5"/>conſiderable is the <hi>Widow her ſelf, whoſe right the Lord will aſſert, and whoſe Cauſe he will plead and manage?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> This now leads me to obſerve, how God hath <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaid, and made good this moſt gracious Title of his, by thoſe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Commands which he hath given forth about them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.17.</note>—Such was <hi>that I juſt now quoted,</hi> wherein he calls upon the <hi>Rulers of</hi> Iſrael, as ever they look'd for mercy at his hand, to <q rend="inline">Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the oppreſſed, judge the Fatherleſs, and plead for the Widow:</q> And ſo the charge to all <hi>earthly Judges</hi> runs, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 82.3. <q rend="inline">Defend the Poor and Fatherleſs, doe juſtice to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and needy.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Tranſgreſſion of this Law of Righteouſneſs,</hi> whoever they be that are found guilty of it, <hi>is ſeverely threatned,</hi> Exod. 22.22, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Ye ſhall not afflict any Widow, or Fatherleſs Child. If thou afflict them in any wiſe, and they cry at all unto me, I will ſurely hear their cry; and my wrath ſhall wax hot, and I will kill you with the Sword; and your wives ſhall be Widows, and your children Fatherleſs,</q> 
               <hi>i.e.</hi> I will <hi>in the ſame kind meet with and requite you.</hi> And the words are <hi>all along Emphatical</hi> on the behalf of <hi>every Widow and Orphan;</hi> If thou afflict them in any wiſe, and if they cry at all unto me, I will hear, I will <hi>ſurely hear,</hi> and be <hi>Wrath upon it;</hi> yea, my Wrath ſhall <hi>wax hot,</hi> and I will retaliate it upon you; I will <hi>kill you with the ſword,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It was one of the <hi>ſolemn Curſes</hi> denounced from mount <hi>Ebal,</hi> to the Equity of which all the people ſubſcribed, <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.9. <q rend="inline">Curſed be he that perverteth the judgment of the Stranger, the Fatherleſs, and the Widow: And all the people ſhall ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And accordingly it is taken notice of in the <hi>Prophets,</hi> as matter of the <hi>higheſt Provocation, and the ominous fore-runner of God's heavieſt Judgments.</hi> So <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.23. <q rend="inline">They judge not the Fatherleſs, neither doth the Cauſe of the Widow come unto them;</q> upon which therefore it follows immediately, <q rend="inline">There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, the mighty are of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Ah!
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103800:6"/>I will eaſe me of mine Adverſaries, and avenge me of mine Enemies:</q> — So alſo, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 5.28. <q rend="inline">They overpaſs the Deeds of the wicked; they judge not the Cauſe, the Cauſe of the Fatherleſs, yet they proſper, and the Right of the needy do they not judge;</q> —upon which therefore it immediately follows: <q rend="inline">Shall not I viſit for theſe things? Shall not my Soul be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this?</q>— And <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.12. <q rend="inline">O houſe of <hi>David!</hi> thus ſaith the Lord, Execute judgment in the morning, and deliver him that is ſpoiled out of the hand of the Oppreſſour, leſt my Fury break out like fire, and burn that none can quench it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the evil of your doings;</q> 
               <hi>which again he repeats,</hi> Chap. 22.3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Execute ye judgment and righteouſneſs, and deliver the ſpoiled out of the hand of the Oppreſſour, and doe no wrong, doe no violence to the Stranger, the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and the Widow; neither ſhed innocent bloud in this place:— But if you will not hear theſe words, I ſwear by my ſelf, ſaith the Lord, that this houſe ſhall become a deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation:</q> — And thus in the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> we find it reckon'd up <hi>by name among thoſe Abominations for which</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>was judged, and burnt as droſs in the fornace,</hi> Chap. 22.7. <q rend="inline">In the midſt of thee have they dealt by Oppreſſion with the Stranger; in thee have they vexed the Fatherleſs, and the Widow:</q> — See it again once more in the Prophet <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary,</hi> Chap. 7.9, 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Thus ſpeaketh the Lord of Hoſts, ſaying, Execute true judgment, and ſhow mercy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions every man to his Brother: And oppreſs not the Widow, nor the Fatherleſs, the Stranger, nor the Poor, and let none of you imagine evil againſt his Brother in his heart:</q> — <q rend="inline">But <hi>(alas! ſaith the Prophet)</hi> they refuſed to hearken, and pulled away the ſhoulder, and ſtopped their ears that they ſhould not hear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> — <q rend="inline">Therefore <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> came a great Wrath from the Lord of Hoſts. Therefore it is come to paſs, that as he cried, and they would not hear, ſo they cried and I would not hear,</q> ſaith the Lord of Hoſts: —Yea, and our <hi>bleſſed Lord and Saviour having ſaid,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Wo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103800:6"/>unto you <hi>Scribes, Phariſees,</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> for you devour Widows houſes, and for a pretence make long prayer:</q> Saint <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.14. adds forthwith upon it, <q rend="inline">Therefore you ſhall receive the greater Damnation,</q> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> upon <hi>both theſe accounts;</hi> firſt for <hi>devouring Widows houſes,</hi> and then doing of it <hi>under a devout pretence, or colour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Pſalmiſt repreſents it as the utmoſt Impiety and Atheiſm together, to commit ſuch an horrid wickedneſs,</hi> and yet to <hi>think that God will connive at it,</hi> Pſal. 44.6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">They ſlay the Widow, and the Stranger, and murther the Fatherleſs:</q> Yet ſay they, the Lord ſhall not ſee, neither ſhall the God of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> regard it: <q rend="inline">Underſtand, O ye Brutiſh among the People, and ye Fools, when will you be wiſe?</q>—</p>
            <p>And it is a <hi>peculiar Curſe which he leaves upon ſome heinous ſinners,</hi> (ſuch eſpecially as had been unmercifull themſelves, and delighted in Curſing others,) that they ſhall <q rend="inline">leave their <hi>Children Fatherleſs,</hi> and their <hi>Wives Widows,</hi>
               </q> and that <hi>in ſo deſtitute and forlorn a condition,</hi> they ſhall <q rend="inline">find <hi>none to pity or relieve them;</hi>
               </q> Pſalm 109.9, 12. — And <hi>ſo likewiſe in the Prophet</hi> Iſaiah, we read, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.17. <q rend="inline">Therefore the Lord ſhall have no joy in their young men, neither ſhall have mercy on their Fatherleſs, and Widows; for every one is an Hypocrite, and an Evil doer.</q> — <q rend="inline">And this is <hi>the Retaliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on particularly threatned unto thoſe who afflict the Fatherleſs, and Widows;</hi>
               </q> and I noted before from <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>But then, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Let it be farther obſerved, <hi>what ſingular care it pleaſed God to take among his People, the</hi> Jews, <hi>in the ſtated Proviſions which he appointed to be made for them;</hi> of which there are <hi>ſundry inſtances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1.) For theſe, by name, it was as well as for the <hi>Levites,</hi> that he allotted the <hi>third year's Tith of their increaſe to be brought in and laid up,</hi> Deut. 14.29. <q rend="inline">And the Levite, becauſe he hath no part, nor inheritance with thee, (as the <hi>other Tribes had,</hi>) and the Fatherleſs, and the Widow within thy Gates,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103800:7"/>ſhall come and eat, and be ſatisfied, that the Lord thy God may bleſs thee in all the work of thine hand which thou doeſt.</q> — For the right underſtanding of which you muſt know, that there was a <hi>firſt Tith</hi> given to the <hi>Levites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Ainſworth <hi>on</hi> Exod. 14.22.</note> out of which they alſo paid a tenth part again to the Prieſts; (<hi>Num.</hi> 18.24, —28. <hi>Nehe.</hi> 10.37, 38.) And then, of that which remained, the owners ſeparated a <hi>ſecond Tith,</hi> which themſelves did eat before the Lord the <hi>firſt and ſecond year;</hi> and this was that which on the <hi>third year</hi> (and ſo on the <hi>ſixth year</hi>) was to be given unto the <hi>Levites, and the Poor here ſpecified:</hi> — Now this third years Tithing had <hi>a ſolemn Confeſſion and Prayer an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to it,</hi> Deut. 26.12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">When thou haſt made an end of Tithing all the Tiths of thy increaſe the third year, which is the year of Tithing, and haſt given it to the Levite, the Stranger, the Fatherleſs, and the Widow, that they may eat within thy Gates, and be filled; then thou ſhalt ſay before the Lord thy God,</q> (viz. <hi>by way of appeal unto him, as Witneſs and Compurgator of thy integrity in the Caſe, and Judge and Avenger, if it be otherwiſe;</hi>) <q rend="inline">I have brought away the hallowed things out of my houſe, and alſo have given them unto the Levite, and unto the Stranger, to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs, and to the Widow, according to all the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which thou haſt commanded me; I have not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed thy Commandments, neither have I forgotten them: Look down from thy Holy habitation from Heaven, and bleſs thy People <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Land which thou haſt given us, as thou ſwareſt unto our Fathers, a Land that floweth with Milk and Honey:</q> [thus regularly claiming the <hi>promiſed Bleſſing</hi> upon their conſcientious performing the condition of it.]</p>
            <p>And the <hi>violation of this Commandment God ſometimes puniſhed them for, with a great Dearth and Famine,</hi> Nehem. 5.3.—13.10. And <hi>unto this that notable expouſtlation in the Prophet</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachi <hi>ſeems to referr,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Dr.</hi> Peacock <hi>on the place.</hi>
               </note> Mal. 3.8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Will a man rob God? yet ye have robed me:</q> But ye ſay, wherein have we robbed thee? In Tiths and Offerings; ye are curſed with a curſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103800:7"/>'this whole Nation. [In this they were generally guilty, that they detain'd part of theſe Tiths, which they ought ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God's Law to have paid, and thereby did abridge God of his due.] <q rend="inline">Bring ye all the Tiths <hi>[therefore, ſaith he]</hi> into the Store-houſe, that there may be meat in my houſe,</q> [not only proviſion for the <hi>daily and annual Sacrifices,</hi> and for the <hi>Priests and Levites waiting on the Altar;</hi> but for the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue alſo of the Poor of God's Family, the Fatherleſs, and the Widow;</hi> who are <hi>mentioned particularly among thoſe, in whoſe behalf he threatens to appear as a ſwift witneſs in judgment againſt them,</hi> verſe 5.] <q rend="inline">And prove me now herewith, ſaith the Lord, if I will not open you the windows of Heaven, and pour you out a Bleſſing, that there ſhall not be room enough to receive it: And I will rebuke the devourer for your ſakes, and he ſhall not deſtroy the fruits of your Ground, neither ſhall your Vine caſt her fruit before the time in the field, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts; and all Nations ſhall call you Bleſſed, for ye ſhall be a delightſome Land, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But then again, (2.) Beſides this, God ſtrictly required a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar regard to be had unto the Fatherleſs, and Widows, in their <hi>ſolemn feaſts every year,</hi> Deut. 16. — So it is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the ſacred Text, for the <hi>Feaſt of Weeks, or Pentecoſt,</hi> verſe 10. <q rend="inline">Thou ſhalt keep the Feaſt of Weeks unto the Lord thy God with a Tribute [<hi>or</hi> ſufficiency, <hi>as the margin reads it</hi>] of a free-will offering of thine hand, which thou ſhalt give unto the Lord thy God, according as the Lord thy God hath bleſſed thee; and thou ſhalt rejoyce before the Lord thy God, thou and thy Son, and thy Daughter, and thy Man-Servant, and thy Maid-Servant; and <hi>(then immediately next to theſe Domeſticks it follows)</hi> the <hi>Levite</hi> that is within thy Gates, and the Stranger, and the Fatherleſs, and the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, that are among you.</q> — So likewiſe for the <hi>feaſt of Tabernacles,</hi> verſe 14. <q rend="inline">And thou ſhall rejoyce in thy Feaſt, thou, and thy Son, and thy Daughter, and thy Man-Servant, and thy Maid-Servant, and the Levite, and the Stranger,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103800:8"/>and the Fatherleſs, and the Widow, that are within thy Gates.</q> And it is <hi>plainly ſignified,</hi> that they were to <hi>rejoyce in ſo doing,</hi> and not to part with their contributions hereunto <hi>grudgingly,</hi> as well knowing, that it was the <hi>way of God's own appointment in order to the ſecuring unto themſelves a greater bleſſing,</hi> ver. 15. <q rend="inline">Seven days ſhalt thou keep a ſolemn Feaſt unto the Lord thy God, in the place which the Lord thy God ſhall chuſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord thy God ſhall bleſs thee in all thy increaſe, and in all the works of thine hands; <hi>Therefore ſhalt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce.</hi>
               </q>—And though it is not <hi>ſo diſtinctly</hi> mention'd in what is ſaid of the <hi>Paſs-over, or Feaſt of unleavened Bread,</hi> yet that alſo is not only to be inferr'd by way of <hi>juſt conſequence,</hi> (it being the <hi>Principal and leading Feaſt,</hi>) but <hi>manifeſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the generall clauſe which follows, and names them all together,</hi> ver. 16, 17. <q rend="inline">Three times a year ſhall all thy Males appear before the Lord thy God in the place which he ſhall chuſe, in the Feaſt of Unleavened Bread, and in the Feaſt of Weeks, and in the Feaſt of Tabernacles, and they ſhall not appear before the Lord empty; Every man ſhall give as he is able, according to the Bleſſing of the Lord thy God, which he hath given thee.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And, according to this Law of theirs <hi>three ſolemn anniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,</hi> the days of <hi>Purim</hi> alſo were afterwards ordained to be <hi>kept yearly,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">As days of Feaſting and Joy, ſending portions to one another, and gifts to the Poor</q> [among <hi>whom,</hi> we may be ſure, the <hi>Fatherleſs and Widow</hi> were not forgotten;] <hi>Eſther</hi> 9.22. And indeed, ſuch are the <hi>moſt proper Gueſts for true and religious Feaſting, whoſe entertainment God himſelf ſtands engaged to ſee abundantly paid for and recompenced,</hi> St. Luk. 14.13, 14. Theſe leaſt deſerve the name of <hi>Feaſts of Charity,</hi> St. Jud. 12.</p>
            <p>But then, (3.) <hi>Over and above this two,</hi> there were <hi>three or four things in their yearly Harveſt allotted to the Poor,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them <hi>chiefly to the Fatherleſs and Widow;</hi> viz. <hi>A nook or corner of the Field,</hi> the <hi>forgotton ſheaf,</hi> the <hi>Gleanings,</hi> and <hi>ſingle or fallen Grapes, and ungathered Olives,</hi> Levit. 19.9, 10. <q rend="inline">When
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103800:8"/>ye reap the Harveſt of your Land, thou ſhalt not wholly reap the corners of thy Field, neither ſhall thou gather the Gleanings of thy Harveſt; And thou ſhalt not glean thy Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, neither ſhalt thou gather every Grape of thy Vineyard, thou ſhalt leave them for the Poor, and Stranger, I am the Lord your God.</q> 
               <hi>Which place we may compare with</hi> Deut. 24.17, &amp;c. <q rend="inline">Thou ſhalt not pervert the Judgment of the Stranger, nor of the Fatherleſs, nor take a Widows Garment to pledge, but thou ſhalt remember that thou waſt a Bondman in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the Lord thy God redeemed thee thence; therefore I command thee to doe this thing. When thou cutteſt down thine Harveſt in the Field, and haſt forgotten a ſheaf in the Field, thou ſhalt not go again to fetch it, it ſhall be for the Stranger, and for the Fatherleſs, and for the Widow, that the Lord thy God may bleſs thee in all the work of thine hands. When thou beateſt thine Olive Tree, thou ſhalt not go over the boughs again; It ſhall be for the Stranger, for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs, and for the Widow. When thou gathereſt the Grapes of thy Vineyard, thou ſhalt not glean it afterwards; It ſhall be for the Stranger, for the Fatherleſs, and for the Widow. And thou ſhalt remember, that thou waſt a Bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the Land of <hi>Egypt:</hi> therefore I command thee to doe this thing.</q>— We cannot but note here, <hi>what a ſtreſs God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty lays upon it,</hi> and how <hi>all along he diſciplin'd the</hi> Jews, <hi>as in a School of continual Charity,</hi> eſpecially towards <hi>the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the Fatherleſs, and the Widow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Let us next obſerve, how he hath thought good ſometimes to <hi>go out of the common road of his Providence, and work ſundry Miracles, on purpoſe to teſtifie and confirm the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reſpects he bears to ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1.) I know not well, whether I ſhould place the <hi>inſtances of</hi> Naomi <hi>and</hi> Ruth <hi>under this Head</hi> of Diſcourſe, or rather have allotted them <hi>one by themſelves.</hi> Sure I am, they were <hi>vertuous and religious Widows,</hi> and left in a <hi>deſolate, distreſſed,</hi> and <hi>poor
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103800:9"/>condition,</hi> and yet by a <hi>wonderful conduct of Divine Providence moſt ſeaſonably relieved, provided for, and advanced,</hi> as may be read at large in the <hi>Book of Ruth,</hi> made up <hi>wholly of this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and which, next to the <hi>clearing of our bleſſed Saviour's Genealogie,</hi> may ſeem to have been written and preſerved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>ſacred Records,</hi> chiefly for the <hi>encouragement of others in all ſucceeding Ages, to become followers of their Piety, Faith, and Patience;</hi> and as a <hi>Book,</hi> I may ſay, <hi>of Peculiar comfort unto Widows in their Afflictions;</hi> The <hi>abſtract</hi> of it is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elimelech,</hi> a Man of ſome note in <hi>Bethlehem-Judah,</hi> with his Wife <hi>Naomi,</hi> and their two Sons, <hi>Mahlon</hi> and <hi>Chilon,</hi> is forced at firſt by a <hi>ſore Famine,</hi> in the time of the <hi>Judges,</hi> to quit his Habitation, and with what moneys he could gather up, to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel and provide ſuſtinence for himſelf and Family in the <hi>Country of Moab,</hi> a <hi>ſtrange and heatheniſh Country.</hi> And there now, not long after, he dies, and leaves <hi>Naomi a ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Widow among ſtrangers:</hi> And there alſo, after this, to the increaſe of her ſorrows, ſhe <hi>Buried her two Sons the only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining ſupports of her Widowhood;</hi> who, during there abode there, had married <hi>two Moabitiſh Women,</hi> now alſo made <hi>diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate Widows, Orpah</hi> and <hi>Ruth.</hi>—<hi>Orpah</hi> upon a little entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, betakes her ſelf to her <hi>own Friends</hi> for maintenance; and we hear no more of her. But <hi>Ruth</hi> reſolves to <hi>abide by her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-in-Law,</hi> whatever became of it, out of love to <hi>her and her Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>two Widows</hi> therefore having ſpent all they had, return together unto <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> entertaining each other with <hi>doleſome complaints</hi> of their <hi>mutual loſſes</hi> as they go; and <hi>God's good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence was all the way over them in that hazardous journey of theirs,</hi> till they came ſafe to the <hi>deſired place.</hi>— But upon their coming <hi>thither,</hi> all the City, ſaith the Text, was moved about them,
<note place="margin">Ch. 1.19.</note> and they ſaid, Is this <hi>Naomi?</hi> That is, ſo ſoon as they had heard the <hi>mournfull ſtory,</hi> and ſeen her great Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and what neceſſities ſhe was reduced unto; How that going out from them in a <hi>wealthy eſtate,</hi> accompanied with her <hi>Husband, and two Sons,</hi> grown up to <hi>manhood,</hi> ſhe was now
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103800:9"/>return'd in ſo <hi>calamitous and deſtitute a condition,</hi> without Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band or Children, or Goods, and only a <hi>young diſtreſſed Widow hanging on her;</hi> They were <hi>all aſtoniſhed,</hi> the <hi>Women eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,</hi> who had formerly known her <hi>in her latter days of Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;</hi> and they could ſcarce <hi>believe their ſenſes,</hi> that this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable object, they now behold, was the <hi>ſame Matron.</hi> Is this <hi>Naomi,</hi> ſay they? And ſhe, hereupon takes the <hi>occaſion offer'd</hi> her, (as paſſion is often <hi>quick and witty</hi> in venting of it ſelf,) to ſhew the ſenſe ſhe lay under of <hi>her own ſad condition. Well may you ask,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Is this <hi>Naomi?</hi> Call me not <hi>Naomi,</hi>
               </q> (<hi>ſaith ſhe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 20, 21.</note> reflecting upon the <hi>ſignification of that name,</hi> that is <hi>pleaſant,</hi> or <hi>delectable</hi>) <q rend="inline">but call me <hi>Marah,</hi> (that is, <hi>Bitter,</hi>) For the Almighty hath dealt very bitterly with me. I went out full, and the Lord hath brought me home empty.</q> [That is, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of all thoſe comforts and means to ſubſiſt on,</hi> which I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had, and <hi>expos'd as you ſee, to want and penury.</hi>] <q rend="inline">Why then call you me <hi>Naomi,</hi> ſeeing the Lord hath teſtified againſt me, and the Almighty hath afflicted me.</q>— But, all this while ſhe thought not of <hi>God's more gracious deſign</hi> in thus <hi>humbling</hi> of her, that in due time he might <hi>raiſe and exalt her.</hi> —Hither his good Providence brought them <hi>at the beginning of Barly Harveſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 22.</note> And ſo the young Widow beſtirs her ſelf immediately <hi>to glean</hi> for the preſent relief both of her ſelf and Mother, in this pinch of their neceſſity. And the <hi>hand of Heaven directs her</hi> (a perfect ſtranger in the Countrey) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>wealthy Kinſman's Field,</hi> whoſe name was <hi>Boaz,</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd his heart alſo to be very kind and compaſſionate towards her;</hi> not only to permit her quietly to <hi>gather after his Reapers,</hi> but to <hi>ſpeak friendly to her,</hi> and <hi>give ſpecial charge to all his Servants about her,</hi> that none ſhould doe her <hi>wrong or Reproach;</hi> Nay, that they ſhould <hi>let ſome handfulls fall on purpoſe for her,</hi> and call her to <hi>eat and drink with them.</hi>—And to <hi>make ſhort,</hi> at laſt, upon farther knowledge and conſideration had of <hi>his Relation to her,</hi> and <hi>her own Vertues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note> according to the <hi>Jewiſh Law and Cuſtome</hi> he charitably <hi>fulfills the right of a neareſt Kinſman,</hi> and <hi>redeems the Land which was left,</hi> and <hi>takes her
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103800:10"/>for his Wife before the Elders in the Gate,</hi> where <hi>all the people accompanied their Marriage with joyful acclamations, and pious good wiſhes;</hi> ver. 11, 12. And <hi>God himſelf bleſſed it, by giving him ſoon after by her a Son, named</hi> Obed, <hi>the Father of</hi> Jeſſe, <hi>and Grand-Father of King</hi> David, of <hi>whoſe Seed</hi> the <hi>Meſſias</hi> was to come, and to be <hi>born too in that City of Bethlehem,</hi> (Saint Matth. 2.5, 6.)—So that by this means, the Pilgrim <hi>Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiſh Widow</hi> became, not only a <hi>Proſelite to the true Religion,</hi> but a <hi>Glorious Mother</hi> in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> And <hi>Aged</hi> Naomi <hi>alſo</hi> is both <hi>comforted</hi> and <hi>exalted with and by her;</hi> made a <hi>joyful Nurſe</hi> to dandle that on her knees, which ſhe was paſt bearing in her Womb; ſees her <hi>Name and Family revived,</hi> after the <hi>loſs of her Husband and Children,</hi> and her <hi>poor Daughter in Law,</hi> who loved her entirely, <hi>better unto her in the Iſſue, than ſeven Sons.</hi> And ſo the <hi>Women,</hi> who at her firſt arrival <hi>lamented and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at her fall and unhappineſs,</hi> did now earneſtly <hi>congratulate the Bleſſed change and alteration of her Fortune,</hi> as we call it, but (if we ſpeak religiouſly) of <hi>God's providence towards her.</hi> Saying, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the birth of the Child;</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Bleſſed be the Lord, which hath not left thee this day without a Kinſman, (or, <hi>Redeemer</hi>) that his name may be famous in <hi>Iſrael!</hi> And he ſhall be unto thee a Reſtorer of thy life, and a nouriſher of thine old age, For thy Daughter-in-Law, which loveth thee, which is better to thee than ſeven Sons, hath born him.</q>—</p>
            <p>You perceive by this time, how deſervedly I call'd this Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>Naomi</hi> and <hi>Ruth, the Widows Book of Conſolation.</hi> I will now paſs on to <hi>ſome more miraculous inſtances of God's eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial favour and goodneſs towards them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Upon this errand <hi>principally</hi> it was, that he ſent <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet unto <hi>Zarephath,</hi> or <hi>Sarrepta, Luke</hi> 4.26. to ſeek relief of the <hi>indigent Widow there,</hi> becauſe he purpoſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite her kindneſs with a <hi>marvellous bleſſing upon her own head,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Ariſe, ſaith God unto him, get thee to <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rephath,</hi> which belongeth to <hi>Zidon,</hi> and dwell there: Behold,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103800:10"/>I have commanded a Widow Woman there to ſuſtain thee.</q> [And <hi>here indeed was the Fountain head of all her ſufficiency.</hi>] <q rend="inline">So he aroſe, and went to <hi>Zarephath,</hi> and when he was come to the gate of the City, behold, the Widow Woman was there gathering of Sticks: And he called to her, and ſaid, fetch me, I pray thee, a little Water in a Veſſel, that I may drink. And as ſhe was going to fetch it, he called to her, and ſaid, bring me, I pray thee, a morſel of bread in thine hand.</q> —<hi>Whereunto when ſhe had mournfully replied,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">As the Lord thy God liveth, I have not a Cake, but an handfull of Meal in a Barrel, and a little Oil in a Cruſe, and behold I am ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering two ſticks, that I may go in and dreſs it for me and my Son, that we may eat it and die.</q> 
               <hi>He preſently anſwered her,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Fear not, go, and doe as thou haſt ſaid: But make me a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Cake thereof firſt, and bring it unto me, and after make for thee and for thy Son.</q> [<hi>Doe me this office of Charity,</hi> and <hi>truſt in God that thou ſhalt be no looſer by it.</hi>] <q rend="inline">For thus ſaith the Lord God of <hi>Iſreal,</hi> the Barrel of Meal ſhall not waſte, neither ſhall the Cruſe of Oil fail, untill the day, that the Lord ſendeth rain upon the Earth,]</q> 
               <hi>viz, to make it bring forth Corn and Oil in abundance.</hi> —Now <hi>obſerve the event:</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">She went, and did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſaying of <hi>Elijah:</hi> And She and He, and her Houſe,]</q> 
               <hi>which ſeems to intimate, that She had more in Family than her Son only,</hi> though <hi>Nature put her upon providing for him before them,]</hi> did eat it many days, the <hi>Margin</hi> reads it <hi>a full year:</hi> and others conjecture, <hi>three years at leaſt,</hi> from what is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd <hi>Ch.</hi> 18.1. of the <hi>third year of the Prophet's being there.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine is ſaid to continue three years and ſix months. Luk. 4, 25. Jam. 5.17.</note> 
               <q rend="inline">And the Barrel of Meal, <hi>ſaith the Text,</hi> waſted not, neither did the Cruſe of Oil fail, according to the word of the Lord, which he ſpoke by <hi>Elijah.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>Such was the reward of this poor Widows Faith and Charity.</hi> And here we have an example, how God can <hi>lengthen out a little, and that our life is ſupported by his word of Bleſſing only.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 8.3. Mat. 4.4.</note> After this the <hi>Widow's Son ſickens, and dies,</hi> ver. 7. and ſhe paſſionately reſents it as a <hi>ſtroke of God's anger,</hi> ſaying <hi>to Elijah,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Oh thou Man of God art thou come unto me, to call my ſin to remembrance, and to ſlay my
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103800:11"/>Son?</q> He therefore, <hi>in pity to her caſe,</hi> (upon a <hi>Divine inſtinct,</hi>) undertakes the <hi>reſtoring of him again.</hi> How his <hi>affections</hi> were moved, you may perceive by <hi>his Prayer, ver.</hi> 20. He cried unto the Lord, and ſaid, <q rend="inline">O Lord my God, haſt thou brought evil upon the Widow, with whom I ſojourn, by ſlaying her Son?</q>—And <hi>then it follows.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">He ſtretched himſelf upon the Child three times, and cried unto the. Lord, and ſaid, O Lord my God, I pray thee let this Child's Soul come into him again. And the Lord heard the voice of <hi>Elijah,</hi> and the Soul of the Child came into him again, and he revived. And <hi>Elijah</hi> took the Child, and brought him down out of the chamber into the houſe, and deliver'd him to his Mother, and <hi>Elijah</hi> ſaid, See, thy Son liveth.</q>— And this is the <hi>firſt we read of in Holy Scripture, that was raiſed up from the dead.</hi> The firſt inſtance is, the <hi>Son of a poor Widow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3.) This Prophet afterwards was taken up into Heaven, and <hi>Eliſha ſucceeded him in a participation of the ſame Spirit,</hi> and he alſo was a <hi>comforter of the Widows.</hi> To this purpoſe we read, <hi>How ſtrangely he multiplyed the diſtreſſed Widows oil for the diſcharge of her Husbands Debts,</hi> and the <hi>Ranſome of her Sons, and her and their future maintenance,</hi> 2 Kings 4.1. <q rend="inline">There cried a certain Woman of the Wives of the Sons of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, [that is, <hi>who had been Wife to one of the Sons of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi>] unto Eliſha, <hi>(who was now Head of their College,)</hi> Saying, Thy Servant my Husband is dead, and thou knoweſt that thy Servant did fear the Lord:</q> (He was, it ſeems, <hi>a very good and Religious man, and known to the Prophet for ſuch,</hi> the <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was her loſs of him:</hi> But this was not all, he <hi>left her in debt.</hi>) <q rend="inline">And the creditor is come, <hi>ſaith ſhe,</hi> to take unto him my two Sons to be Bondmen.</q>—<hi>This deplorable caſe now moves the Prophet to ſay unto her.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">What ſhall I doe for thee? Tell me, what haſt thou in the houſe. And ſhe ſaid, thine Handmaid hath not any thing in the houſe, <hi>(viz. of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as to raiſe money from,)</hi> ſave a pot of Oil.</q> (<hi>A poor ſtock!</hi> but <hi>enough for that power to work upon, which can create out of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103800:11"/>nothing.</hi>] <q rend="inline">Then he ſaid, go, borrow thee Veſſels of all thy neighbours, even empty Veſſels; borrow not a few; (or <hi>ſcant not.</hi>) And, when thou art come in, thou ſhalt ſhut the door upon thee and thy Sons, and thou ſhalt pour out into all theſe Veſſels, and thou ſhalt ſet aſide that which is full.</q>—<hi>And now, let us note the ſucceſs:</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">So ſhe went from him, and ſhut the door upon her, and upon her Sons, who brought the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels to her, and ſhe poured out; and it came to paſs when the Veſſels were full, that ſhe ſaid unto her Son, <hi>(one of her Sons then next her,)</hi> bring me yet a Veſſel; and he ſaid unto her, there is not a Veſſel more. And the oil ſtayed,</q> 
               <hi>viz. That there might be no waſte, having run freely as long as there was any thing to receive it in.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Then ſhe came and told the man of God.</q> 
               <hi>Gratefully acknowledging the miracle wrought for her.</hi>—<q rend="inline">And he ſaid, go, ſell the Oil, and pay thy debt, and live thou and thy Children on the reſt.</q>—Such was the <hi>bounty of God by</hi> Eliſha, <hi>to this Prophet's Widow, exceeding her firſt requeſt.</hi> She was ſollicitous <hi>only for the redemption of her Children from the credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors Arreſt:</hi> But ſhe receives, wherewithall both to <hi>diſcharge the debt her Husband left her in,</hi> and <hi>provide a competency for her ſelf and her children to ſubſiſt a while upon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Unto theſe inſtances now, I will annex <hi>that Miracle of our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour,</hi> the great Prophet whom <hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>Eliſha</hi> were but Types of, <hi>recorded in the New Teſtament, St.</hi> Luk. 7.11, 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">It came to paſs, that he went into a City called <hi>Naim,</hi> and many of his Diſciples went with him and much People. Now when he came nigh to the gates of the City; behold there was a dead man carried out, the onely Son of his Mother, and ſhe was a Widow:</q> This was the <hi>compaſſionableneſs of the caſe. A deſolate Widow, following the Corpſe of her Son,</hi> her <hi>onely Son, the ſtay of her Age,</hi> the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of her Widow-hood, to the grave:</hi> And it was <hi>matter of general Lamentation among her neighbours alſo,</hi> for much Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the City was with her.—<q rend="inline">And when the Lord ſaw her, <hi>(ſaith the Evangeliſt, his Bowels too were moved,)</hi> he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103800:12"/>had Compaſſion on her, and ſaid unto her, weep not:</q> — But alas! <hi>Good words alone were not able to chear up one in her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition;</hi> and therefore unto thoſe he forthwith adds <hi>a miracle of Beneficience;</hi> and indeed moſt of his miraculous Works were of <hi>this nature,</hi> ſo many <hi>Evidences of his divine Power in ſhewing mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and doing good:</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">And he came and touched the bier, (or <hi>Coſſin,</hi>) and they that bare him ſtood ſtill; and he ſaid, young man, I ſay unto thee ariſe; <hi>[thus he commanded his Soul into his Body again;]</hi> and he that was dead ſate up, and he began to ſpeak, and he deliver'd him to his Mother:</q> — Whereby he did not only <hi>ſtay her Tears,</hi> but <hi>turn'd her mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into Joy and Gladneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now this inſtance prompts me to obſerve, in the <hi>fifth place,</hi> That <hi>God hath planted ſoft and tender Hearts, or natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Bowels in the generality of men</hi> (who have not <hi>out-ſinn'd their Humanity</hi>) to reſent the ſad Circumſtances of the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows and Fatherleſs; but <hi>theſe in good men are in a more eminent manner renew'd and improv'd,</hi> who are required to <hi>put on as the Elect of God, Bowels of Mercy and Kindneſs,</hi> Coloſ. 3.12.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Rhetorick</hi> there is in the <hi>naked Repreſentation of ſo deſtitute an eſtate,</hi> is viſible in <hi>that parable, which the wiſe Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of</hi> Tekoah <hi>artificially uſed to move King</hi> David <hi>to recall</hi> Abſolom, 2 Sam. 14.4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">She fell on her face to the ground, and did obeiſance, and ſaid, Help, O King! And the King ſaid unto her, what aileth thee? And ſhe anſwered and ſaid, <hi>I am indeed a Widow woman, and mine Husband is dead,</hi> and thine Handmaid had two Sons, and they two ſtrove together in the field, and there was none to part them; but the one ſmote the other, and ſlew him: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the whole Family is riſen againſt thine Handmaid, and they ſaid, deliver him that ſmote his Brother, that we may kill him for the Life of his Brother, whom he ſlew; and we will deſtroy the Heir alſo; and ſo they ſhall <hi>quench my Coal which is left, and ſhall not leave to my Husband, neither name nor remainder upon the Earth:</hi> — And the King ſaid
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103800:12"/>to the Woman, go to thine houſe, and I will give charge concerning thee:</q> — There <hi>needed not any farther requeſt,</hi> than what the caſe it ſelf made for her.</p>
            <p>But then, a <hi>Widow's Importunity is capable of adding much hereunto:</hi> To which purpoſe we are inſtructed from <hi>our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Parable of the Importunate Widow,</hi> who <hi>wearied out a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and unjuſt judge, (who neither feared God, nor regarded man,) by her continual ſollicitations, to take pity on her, St.</hi> Luke 18. Upon which the Evangeliſt gives us alſo <hi>our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Remark:</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">And the Lord ſaid, hear what the unjuſt judge ſaith: And ſhall not God avenge his own Elect, which cry day and night to him, though he bear long with them? I tell you that he will avenge them ſpeedily.—</q>
            </p>
            <p>But we will turn from him to a <hi>much better man;</hi> a man that hath the Teſtimony from God himſelf, of being <hi>perfect and upright, fearing God, and eſchewing Evil,</hi> Job 1.1. 'Tis the expreſſion he deſcribes the <hi>utmoſt ſtretch of wickedneſs, and oppreſſion by,</hi> Job 24.3, 4. <q rend="inline">They drive away the Aſs of the Fatherleſs, they take the Widow's Ox for a Pledge, they turn the Needy out of the way; the Poor of the Earth hide themſelves together.</q> 
               <hi>And again,</hi> verſe 21, <q rend="inline">He doth not good to the Widow:</q> — And <hi>Eliphaz indeed had charged him with this horrid guilt, as the cauſe of his preſent Calamities,</hi> Chap. 22.9, 10. <q rend="inline">Thou haſt ſent Widows away empty, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> and the Arms of the Fatherleſs have been broken: Therefore ſnares are round about thee, and ſudden fear trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth thee:</q> — But <hi>the good man was of quite another Character and Practice;</hi> and therefore had <hi>juſt occaſion upon this injurious Charge to make mention of it for his own Apology,</hi> Chap. 29.12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">I deliver'd the Poor that cried, <hi>(ſaith he,)</hi> the Fatherleſs, and him that had none to help him; the Bleſſing of him which was ready to periſh came upon me; and I caus'd the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow's Heart to ſing for joy:</q> — <hi>Yea, and he appeals to God for his witneſs in this matter, and denounceth a moſt heavy Impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation againſt himſelf, ſhould he have been found to have done otherwiſe,</hi> Chap. 31.16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">If I have with held the Poor
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103800:13"/>from their deſire, or have cauſed the eyes of the Widow to fail, or have eaten my morſel my ſelf alone, and the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs have not eaten thereof; (for from my Youth he was brought up with me, and I have guided her) <hi>that is, the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,</hi> (from my Mother's Womb;) if I have ſeen any periſh for want of Clothing; or any Poor without Covering; if his Loins have not bleſſed me, and if he were not warmed with the Fleece of my Sheep; if I have lift up my hands againſt the Fatherleſs, when I ſaw my help in the gate; then let mine Arm fall from my Shoulder-blade, and mine Arm be broken from the Bone:</q> 
               <hi>[i. e. as I am falſly traduced to have ſerved the Fatherleſs:]</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 22.9.</note> No, I had a <hi>greater dread upon me of the Divine Vengeance, than to dare to venture on ſuch a piece of inſolence:</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">For deſtruction from God was a Terror to me, and by reaſon of his Highneſs I could not endure:</q> — This alone would have reſtrain'd him, had nothing elſe; but it was more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over <hi>clean contrary to the biaſs of his Temper and Inclination, who looked upon the meaneſt of his Servants as his Fellow-Brethren and Siſters;</hi> and therefore reckon'd with himſelf that he could <hi>never anſwer it to their common Father, ſhould he wrong or abuſe any one of them,</hi> as he had ſaid juſt before, <hi>verſe</hi> 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">If I did deſpiſe the Cauſe of my Man-Servant, or of my Maid-Servant, when they contended with me; what then ſhall I doe when God riſeth up; and when he viſiteth what ſhall I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him? Did not he that made me in the womb, make him?</q> And did not one faſhion us in the Womb?] that is, plainly, have we not <hi>all one Father?</hi> Are we not <hi>all the ſame Fleſh and Bloud?</hi> But now, if there be found <hi>ſo much goodneſs and compaſſion in Men;</hi> who at beſt have <hi>their Defects and Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections;</hi> how <hi>much more is there in God?</hi> Tis <hi>the way of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which our Bleſſed Saviour hath taught us for our great encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement,</hi> St. Matth. 7.11. <q rend="inline">If ye then being evil, know how to give good gifts unto your Children; <hi>how much more</hi> ſhall your Father which is in Heaven, give good things to them that ask him?</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:103800:13"/>
            <p>This goodneſs of Nature is but a <hi>Beam from his Sun,</hi> or a <hi>drop from his Fountain:</hi> — And this is yet <hi>farther advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the World by the Principles of Chriſtianity;</hi> which urge us to the <hi>perfection of Charity;</hi> and there cannot certainly be a <hi>fitter Object</hi> of it, than the <hi>diſtreſſed Widow and Fatherleſs:</hi> Such a charity was <hi>Tabitha,</hi> or <hi>Dorcas; a Diſciple of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's at</hi> Joppa, <hi>famous for</hi> Acts 9.36. <q rend="inline">This woman was full of good Works, and Alms-deeds which ſhe did;</q> who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>ſickening and dying,</hi> the Diſciples there, upon ſo great a loſs, ſent preſently for St. <hi>Peter</hi> to come to them; and when he was come he found <hi>all the Widows ſtanding by weeping, and ſhewing the Coats and Garments which</hi> Dorcas <hi>made while ſhe was with them:</hi> — And this proved <hi>an effectual motive to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of her Reſuſcitation;</hi> the <hi>reſtoring of ſo ſerviceable a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to the Church:</hi> — And this now is made by St. <hi>James,</hi> the Proof and Tryal of the <hi>Purity of our Religion,</hi> Chap. 1.27. <q rend="inline">Pure Religion and undefiled before God, even the Father, is this <hi>(ſaith he,)</hi> to viſit the Fatherleſs and Widows in their affliction;]</q> — that, as we have experienced, the <hi>goodneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eraſ. <hi>Par.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and great Mercy, and Beneficence of God towards our ſelves;</hi> ſo we alſo ſhew the ſame in all the inſtances we can towards thoſe who are <hi>moſt neceſſitous,</hi> and from whom we can expect the <hi>leaſt requital.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> I will cloſe theſe Scripture Obſervations with a brief reflexion upon the <hi>ſpecial regard both of Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles unto theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> I have already inſtanced in his Compaſſion to the <hi>Widow of</hi> Naim, <hi>in raiſing up her onely Son:</hi> But you may note farther with me, (1.) That he <hi>honoured a Widow with the manifeſtation of himſelf in the Temple;</hi> when, according to the prediction of the Prophets, he made his firſt <hi>appearance there, St.</hi> Luke 2.36, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (2.) That he <hi>admired, and commended the poor Widow's mites of Charity, above all the richer one's Oblations, St.</hi> Mark 12.41, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">And Jeſus ſat over againſt the Treaſury, and beheld how the People caſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103800:14"/>money into the Treaſury: And there came a certain poor Widow, and ſhe threw in two Mites, which make a Farthing: And he called unto him his Diſciples, and ſaith unto them; Verily I ſay unto you, that this poor Widow hath caſt more in than all they which have caſt into the Treaſury; for all they did caſt in of their aboundance, but ſhe of her want did caſt in all that ſhe had, even all her Living:</q> — And this I the <hi>rather note,</hi> becauſe a principal grievance of good and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perſons, when reduced to a low Eſtate, is uſually this; <hi>that they have not wherewith to doe the works of Charity, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they did, or others doe:</hi> Whereas from hence they may gather, <hi>how graciouſly God will accept and reward the meaneſt of their offerings,</hi> and <hi>take the Will for the Deed from them:</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the condition and circumſtances he hath brought them to. — (3.) That he <hi>recommended ſuch Gueſts eſpecially to the Feaſts of Charity:</hi> I touched on this occaſionally before; but here I will <hi>tranſcribe the Text for it, St.</hi> Luke 14.12, 13, 14. <q rend="inline">When thou makeſt a Dinner, or Supper, <hi>(ſaith he,)</hi> call not thy Friends, nor thy Brethren, neither thy Kinſmen, nor thy rich Nighbours; leſt they alſo bid thee again, and a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe be made thee:]</q> 
               <hi>This is only a Traffick, or Merchandiſe, and Exchange of Courteſies and Civilities,]</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">But when thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt a Feaſt call the Poor, the Maimed, the Lame, and the Blind, and thou ſhalt be Bleſſed, for they cannot recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe thee; for thou ſhalt be recompenſed at the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Juſt.]</q> This is the <hi>genuine Hoſpitality which makes God himſelf a Debtor to his Creatures; and for which he undertakes that it ſhall not loſe it's reward.</hi> — (4.) <hi>That he took all opportunities to inculcate, and enlarge upon the precepts of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity:</hi>—(1.) <hi>When ſome had Indignation at the good Woman's coſt who annointed him, upon a pretence that the ointment might have been ſold for much, and given to the poor; he ſo vindicates her kindneſs, as to allow alſo of that Charity which they preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to:</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Jeſus ſaid, why trouble you the Woman; ſhe hath wrought a good work on me: For you have the Poor with you always, and whenſoever ye will ye may doe them good; but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103800:14"/>me ye have not always, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> compare St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.10, 11. <hi>with</hi> St. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.6, 7. <hi>Where he ſeems to refer to what was ſaid in the Law,</hi> Deut. 15.11. <q rend="inline">The Poor ſhall never ceaſe out of the Land; therefore I command thee, ſaying, <hi>thou ſhalt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen thine hand wide</hi> unto thy Brother, to thy Poor, and to thy needy in the Land. And in another place; Give to him that asketh, ſaith he, and from him that would borrow of thee, turn thou not away,</q> St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.42. Which was alſo the <hi>preſcription of the Law,</hi> Deut. 15.8. — (2.) He <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten cites and approves of the great Commandment;</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Thou ſhalt love thy Nighbour as thy ſelf;</q> and he tells a <hi>particular ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or parable,</hi> to ſhew them, <hi>that every one in neceſſity, and not a Jew only, was to be looked upon as our Nighbour;</hi> and having therein mention'd <hi>a compaſſionate and merciful</hi> Samaritan, bids all to imitate him: <q rend="inline">Go, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> and doe thou likewiſe,</q> 
               <hi>Saint</hi> Luke 10.30. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — (3.) He gives an <hi>admirable Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe upon this Command, and ſuch as would be a perpetual relief to the Widow, and Fatherleſs, particularly in that golden Rule of his, St.</hi> Matth. 7.12. <q rend="inline">All things whatſoever ye would that men ſhould doe unto you, doe you even ſo to them; for this, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> is the Law, and the Prophets.</q> — (4.) He <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends ſecret Alms, with the aſſurance, that our Father who ſees in ſecret ſhall reward them openly, St.</hi> Matth. 6.4. And elſewhere he aſſerts, <hi>that whoſoever giveth to any one of his Diſciples a Cup of cold water only, in the name of a Diſciple, ſhall in no wiſe loſe his Reward, St.</hi> Matth. 10.42. That is, he that doth the <hi>leaſt kindneſs on that ſcore</hi> to them, ſhall be ſure of a <hi>Retribution</hi> for it. — (5.) In other places he <hi>calls upon them that are rich and able,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">to lay up their Treaſures in Heaven, where neither moth nor ruſt corrupt, nor Thieves break through and ſteal,</q> St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.20, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as St. <hi>Luke</hi> hath it; <q rend="inline">To provide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves bags which wax not old, a Treaſure in the Heavens that faileth not,</q> St. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.33. And, <hi>as prudent Stewards of their aboundance,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">to make themſelves friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs, [which is <hi>truly ſo, when with-held from Charitable uſes;</hi>] that when they fail they may receive them
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103800:15"/>into everlaſting habitations,</q> St. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.9. — (6.) And which is <hi>moſt of all conſiderable;</hi> he acquaints us, that in the <hi>laſt day,</hi> when he ſhall come to <hi>judge the World,</hi> and <hi>doom all men to their eternal, and unalterable eſtate of Happineſs, or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery,</hi> he will <hi>proceed eſpecially by their omiſſion, or practice of the Laws of Charity,</hi> and interpret the doing, or not doing of it to the <hi>leaſt and moſt deſpiſed Chriſtian,</hi> as done or not done to <hi>himſelf, St.</hi> Matth. 25. — (7.) Once more yet, obſerve, that while he was <hi>hanging upon the Croſs, and amidſt his Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments there,</hi> he was nevertheleſs <hi>mindfull of a comfortable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for his deſolate Mother after his departure, St.</hi> John 19.26, 27. <q rend="inline">When Jeſus ſaw his Mother, and the Diſciple whom he loved, ſtanding by; he ſaid unto his Mother, Woman, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy Son; And to that Diſciple, behold thy Mother. And from that hour, <hi>ſaith the Evangeliſt,</hi> that Diſciple took her to his own Home.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And now, in the <hi>next place,</hi> for the <hi>Apoſtles of our Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> it ſhall ſuffice to <hi>note,</hi> that they appointed <hi>a daily Miniſtration for poor Widows; and when the number of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed,</hi> ordained an order of men, by the name of <hi>Deacons, particularly to attend on that work,</hi> Acts 6. And <hi>St.</hi> Paul <hi>hath left eſpecial Rules concerning them,</hi> 1 Tim. 5. As for them who had <hi>Children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſe 4.</note> 
               <hi>or Nephews, able to doe for them:</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">He requires that they learn firſt to <hi>ſhew Piety or Kindneſs at home, and</hi> requite their Parents; for that <hi>ſaith he,</hi> is good and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table before God:</q>
               <note place="margin">verſe 3.</note> But as for them who were <hi>Widows indeed,</hi> That they ſhould have an <hi>Honourable maintainance out of the publick ſtock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After which I ſhall not mention thoſe many <hi>Hoſpitals, and Alms-houſes, and Funds of Charity,</hi> which God hath excited ſeveral worthy Benefactors to <hi>erect, and contribute to,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account, throughout the <hi>Chriſtian World:</hi> And will only <hi>add,</hi> that the <hi>Liturgy of the Church hath in all ages been mindfull of them,</hi> and <hi>recommended them by name unto God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty;</hi> as we <hi>ſtill retain it in our excellent Litany:</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">That it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103800:15"/>may pleaſe thee to defend and provide for the Fatherleſs Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Widows, and all that are deſolate and oppreſſed. We beſeech thee to hear us, Good Lord!</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore, ſo long as there is a <hi>God,</hi> who with a <hi>Paternal Providence</hi> preſides over and governs the World, who is a <hi>very preſent help in Trouble,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 25.4.</note> and (as the <hi>Prophet Iſaiah ſpeaks</hi>) <hi>a ſtrength to the poor, a ſtrength to the needy in his diſtreſs, a refuge from the ſtorm,</hi> and <hi>a ſhadow from the heat, a Father to the Fatherleſs,</hi> (as hath been ſhewed,) and <hi>an Husband to the Widow:</hi> And ſo long as there <hi>are men of compaſſions, or men truly and ſincerely religious left; a Church of God, and genuine Chriſtian upon Earth,</hi> the Widows and Fatherleſs may reſt ſecure of it; that they ſhall not be <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forſaken, or deſtitute:</hi> They have an Heavenly Father and Friend, who is <hi>All-ſufficient, evermore with them;</hi> who knows what is really <hi>beſt and moſt profitable for them,</hi> and wanteth not for <hi>Wiſdom, or Power, or Goodneſs,</hi> to relieve them;
<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.63.16.</note> an <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Father and Husband,</hi> infinitely <hi>beyond all others.</hi> And they have as many <hi>Brethren and Siſters</hi> to ſympathize with them, as there are <hi>Good men and Chriſtians,</hi> to whom their Caſe is made known.</p>
            <p>Let them take notice of that <hi>eminent Title of Grace,</hi> whereby God is peculiarly acknowledged and addreſs'd unto, <hi>under the New Teſtament:</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">The Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, from whom the whole Family in Heaven and Earth is named,</q> 
               <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.14, 15. That is, <hi>in ſhort,</hi> the <hi>Father of Christ, and all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi> as <hi>he ſaid before his Aſcention,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Go to my Brethren, and ſay unto them; I aſcend unto my Father and your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to my God and your God,</q> St. <hi>John</hi> 20.17.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi>] by a <hi>natural and inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable generation,</hi> who is therefore call'd his <hi>own, his Onely-begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, his Dearly-beloved Son, born before all the Creation:</hi> And <q rend="inline">he that ſpar'd not his own Son, but deliver'd him up for us all;</q> how ſhall he not with him alſo freely give us all things? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. Or what <hi>good thing</hi> will he now deny us, which we ask in the <hi>prevailing name, and for the ſake and merits of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103800:16"/>this Son of his Love, who died for us,</hi> and ever lives to make <hi>interceſſion on our behalf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then <hi>through him our Father alſo,] of whom the whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily in Heaven and Earth is named,]</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> on <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>that is, the whole World, Gentiles as well as Jews, are now acknowledged for his Children by ſpecial Adoption and Grace, his ſelect and peculiar Houſhold; who are never from under his Eye and Care; whom as he hath commanded others,</hi> Galat. 16.10. <hi>ſo he will much more himſelf, eſpecially upon all opportunities,</hi> doe good unto the Houſhold of Faith.</p>
            <p>I will conclude with the good and ſeaſonable <hi>Advice, Firſt of our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour,</hi> and then of his <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> The Leſſon from our Bleſſed Saviour, is <hi>that of his Sermon on the Mount,</hi> as it is called, St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Take no thought for your Life, [that is, <hi>no unbelieving, anxious, corroding, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieting, or diſturbing Thought,]</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">what ye ſhall eat, or what ye ſhall drink; nor yet for your Body, what ye ſhall put on.</q> (1.) <q rend="inline">Is not the Life more than Meat, and the Body than Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</q> [that is, <hi>Have you not in hand a pledge of what is greater than that you are apt to be ſollicitous for?</hi> He that gave and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues your Life, cannot he as eaſily give you Meat? And he that made and maintains your Body, cannot he alſo as eaſily cloath it]? (2.) <hi>Touching Food,</hi>) <q rend="inline">Behold the Fowls of the Air, for they ſow not, neither do they reap, nor gather into Barns; yet your Heavenly Father feedeth them;</q> Are ye not much better than they? [may you not therefore <hi>much rather reſt ſecure of his Bleſſing upon your ordinary prudence, and induſtry?</hi>] (3.) <q rend="inline">Which of you by taking thought can add one Cubite to his Stature?</q> [And is it not then a manifeſt point of Folly, to trouble and moleſt your ſelves with <hi>that, which is no ways beneficial, and advantageous; but many ways are hurtfull to you?</hi>] (4.) <q rend="inline">And why take ye thought for Raiment? Conſider the Lilies of the field, how they grow; they toil not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they ſpin; and yet I ſay to you, that even <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his Glory was not array'd like one of theſe:</q> [The greateſt <hi>Art</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:103800:16"/>falls ſhort of Nature's <hi>work,</hi> and the beſt of <hi>humane skill and cunning</hi> is infinitely below the meaneſt inſtances of <hi>Divine Power and Wiſdom;</hi>] <q rend="inline">Wherefore if God ſo cloath the Graſs of the Field, which to day is, and to morrow is caſt into the Oven, <hi>[and there is an end of it]</hi> ſhall he not much more cloath you, <hi>[being of an Higher form, a far more conſiderable rank, and made for immortality,]</hi> O ye of little Faith? — Therefore take no thought, ſaying what ſhall we eat, or what ſhall we drink, or wherewithall ſhall we be cloathed:</q> For (5.) <q rend="inline">after all theſe things do the Gentiles ſeek.</q> [The <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, who want your Light of Knowledge, whoſe Portion and Hopes are confined to this life only, and who live without a Senſe of God and his Providence in the World; make theſe the Object of their continual Sollicitude:]</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">For (6.) your Heavenly Father know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that you have need of all theſe things;</q> [you have <hi>a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and ſo of <hi>goodneſs,</hi> an <hi>Heavenly Father,</hi> and ſo of <hi>Power ſufficient</hi> to relieve you; and <hi>none of your wants or neceſſities are hid from him.</hi> He knows <hi>what you ſtand moſt in need of, and what ſupply is moſt fitting for you, and when is the moſt ſeaſonable time for it:</hi> Nay, and you have <hi>his promiſe,</hi> if you be not wanting to <hi>that great and principal buſineſs, he hath given you in charge to mind.</hi>] <q rend="inline">(7.) But ſeek ye firſt the Kingdom of God, and his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you:</q> [Take but care of <hi>your Chriſtian Duty, and God will provide for the Reſt. Faithfull is he that hath promiſed, and you may relie upon him for it.</hi>] Thus you are not to diſquiet and trouble your ſelves for your <hi>preſent proviſion,</hi> much leſs to <hi>enlarge your cares and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns for a long while to come: — So he proceeds;</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Take no thought therefore for the morrow; for (1) the morrow ſhall take thought for the things of it ſelf.</q> [You are <hi>not ſure of the morrow, or what ſhall befall you on it;</hi> you know not, <hi>what a day may bring forth:</hi> 'Tis <hi>time enough to look after that, when it comes.</hi>] (2) Sufficient unto the day is the evil thereof. [You need not <hi>anticipate Labour and Affliction,</hi> every day brings <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough with it to Exerciſe both your Patience and Diligence;</hi> to <hi>watch againſt the Evils of Temptation</hi> that aſſault you; and to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103800:17"/>
               <hi>bear the evils of calamity and affliction,</hi> that may light upon you. This you ſee is an <hi>incomparable diſcourſe,</hi> and <hi>full of moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull Arguments and Conſiderations to eaſe and quiet our Minds,</hi> if we attend as we ought unto them.—And hereunto I would have you add <hi>his Farewell Sermon,</hi> as it may be ſtyled <hi>to his droo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Diſciples, when he was about to take his leave of them, in the</hi> 14.15 and 16 Chapt. of St. <hi>John</hi> too long for me in this place to <hi>write over,</hi> or <hi>gloſs upon,</hi> — I will <hi>but touch here and there.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Let not your heart be troubled:
<note place="margin">Ch. 14.1. Verſe 2.3.</note> ye believe in God, believe alſo in me. I go to prepare a place for you: And if I go and propare a place for you, I will come again, and receive you unto my ſelf, that where I am, ye may be alſo. Whatſoever ye ſhall ask in my Name,
<note place="margin">Verſe 13.</note> that will I doe, that the Father may be glorified in the Son.
<note place="margin">Verſe 15. Verſe 16.</note>—If ye love me, keep my Commandments; And I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever.
<note place="margin">Verſe 18.</note>—I will not leave you comfortleſs, <hi>(or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans as the margin reads it,)</hi> I will come to you. —If a man love me,
<note place="margin">Verſe 23.</note> he will keep my words, and my Father will love him, and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him.</q>—How can they be <hi>ſolitary,</hi> whom <hi>each of the three Perſons engage thus graciouſly to viſit and dwell with?</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you; not as the world giveth, give I unto you: Let not your heardbe troubled, neither let it be affraid.—Theſe things have I ſpoken to you, that my joy might remain in you, and that your joy might be full.—If the world hate you, ye know that it hated me before it hated you.—Remember the word that I ſaid unto you, The Servant is not greater than the Lord. — Ye ſhall be ſorrowfull, but your ſorrow ſhall be turned into Joy:—And your joy no man taketh away from you.—Theſe things I have ſpoken unto you, that in me ye might have peace, in the World ye ſhall have tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: but be of good chear, I have overcome the World.</q>
            </p>
            <p>After all which, he <hi>betakes himſelf to Prayer,</hi> Chap. 17. To teach us, <hi>what we ſhould doe alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:103800:17"/>
            <p>And unto <hi>this</hi> now <hi>Saint</hi> Paul <hi>directs us,</hi> as the <hi>moſt effectuall cure of all our griefs and troubles,</hi> Philip. 4, 6, 7. <q rend="inline">Be carefull for nothing, but in every thing by Prayer and Supplication let your requeſts be made known to God; And the Peace of God, which paſſeth all our underſtanding, ſhall keep your hearts and minds through Chriſt Jeſus.</q> To which I will only ſubjoyn St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Counſel, 1. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5, 6, 7. <q rend="inline">Humble your ſelves under the mighty hand of God, that may exalt you in due time; caſting all your care upon him, for he careth for you.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To whom now be Glory, and Dominion for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>The Diſtreſſed Widows Prayer.</head>
            <q>
               <p>MOST Gracious God, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, of whom the whole Family in Heaven and Earth is named; who knoweſt what things we ſtand in need of before we ask; and art able to doe exceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly above all that we ask or think; and haſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to hear the Prayers of thy Children and Servants in their diſtreſſes: Upon this encouragement I do now proſtrate my ſelf before the Throne of thy Grace, that I may obtain Mercy, and find Grace for my ſeaſonable help in this time of need. I humble my Soul, with all the ſubmiſſion I can, under the ſenſe of thy mighty Hand, which hath reduced me to this afflicted condition. Thou Lord haſt given, and thou haſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away; for ever Bleſſed be thy Name! Good and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous art thou in all thy diſpoſals, and haſt a Sovereign un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Power to doe with thine own Creatures as it pleaſeth thee. Not <hi>what I would,</hi> but what thou wilt; not <hi>as I would,</hi> but as thou wilt: Not my ſinfull and fooliſh Will, but thy All-wiſe and Holy Will be done. Yea, I will bear
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:103800:18"/>thy indignation, O Lord, becauſe I have ſinned againſt thee. It is of thy Mercies, that I am not conſumed: Wherefore ſhould the living complain, and that for the puniſhment of their Sins, who are always puniſhed leſs than their iniquities deſerve? Sanctifie, I beſeech thee, all the dealings of thy Providence towards me, that it may be good for me in the Iſſue to have been afflicted; and however grievous my loſs and ſufferings are unto me for the preſent, they may bring forth the peaceable fruits of Righteouſneſs, when I ſhall have, during thy pleaſure, been exerciſed with them: In the mean while, I pray thee, ſupport and ſtrengthen me by thy Holy Spirit with all might in the inward man, unto all patience and long-ſuffering with joyfulneſs; Raiſe me up a ſupply of Friends to pity and compaſſionate my forlorn and deſtitute eſtate, and do thou reward all their kindneſſes. Provide for me and mine, as it ſhall ſeem beſt unto thee, the Food which is convenient for us, our daily Bread; and give us Contentment with, and Thankfulneſs for thy Allowances, whatſoever they are. Lord, I believe, help thou my unbelief, and increaſe my Faith in thy All-ſufficiency, who art every where with me; a Refuge unto which I may always reſort, a ſtrong Tower, into which I may run to be ſafe. Protect and defend me from all evil Temptations, and grant that I may doe nothing at any time to offend or diſpleaſe Thee, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeit that Bleſſed Privilege which thou giveſt me in thy Holy Word, of applying to, and reſting on thee in my preſent cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, under that moſt comfortable Title of the Patron of Widows, and Father of the Fatherleſs. Make me a fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower of Holy and Godly Matrons, and thoſe Widows indeed whom thou putteſt Honour upon, who truſt in thee, and ſerve thee, continuing in Prayers and Supplications night and day.</p>
               <p>Hear the voice of my Sighs and Tears; Let my cry come unto thee, O Thou that heareſt Prayer, and art a preſent help in the day of trouble, and deal with thine Handmaid according to the multitude of thy tender mercies, for the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:103800:18"/>merit ſake of thy dearly Beloved Son, Jeſus Chriſt the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, the Propitiation for our Sins, and our Advocate at thy right Hand; To whom with thee, O Bleſſed Father, and thy Holy Spirit of Grace and Comfort, be all Honour and Glory World without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why art thou caſt down, O my Soul, and why art thou diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted within me? Hope thou in God: For I ſhall yet praiſe him, who is the health of my contenance and my God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O God, my Soul is caſt down within me: therefore will I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thee.—I will ſay unto God, my Rock, why haſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten me?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why art thou caſt down, O my Soul? And why art thou diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted within me?</hi> &amp;c. </p> 
                  <bibl>Pſal 42.5, 6, 9, 11. - 43.5.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
